A Guide to the Edith Francisco Buckley papers, 1908-2013
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Edith Francisco Buckley papers, 1908-2013
The Library of Virginia
50846
8.5 cu. ft. and 18 boxes and one folder
Edith Francisco Buckley
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Edith Francisco Buckley of Fairfax, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Edith Francisco Buckley was a founder of the Society for the Descendants of Peter Francisco in 1971 and has served as an officer of the society for most of its existence. Edith Francisco was born in Louisa County, Virginia. She married Ralph E. Buckley in 1942 and they had one son. Edith Francisco Buckley attended Mary Washington College of the University of Virginia (now the University of Mary Washington) and worked in education. She later worked for American Airlines in a variety of positions. Buckley is a member of the Daughters of the American Revolution and is a published poet.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1908-2013, of Edith Francisco Buckley of Fairfax, Virginia, concerning her ancestor Peter Francisco (1760-1831) and the Society of the Descendants of Peter Francisco. Collection documents Buckley's and the Society's efforts to discover and record Francisco's life and Revolutionary War service, as well as to trace his descendants.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Society of the Descendants of Peter Francisco
Series III: Individuals
Series IV: Photographs and images
Series V: Addresses and talks
Series VI: Clippings
Series VII: Peter Francisco biography
Series VIII: Genealogy
Series IX: Portuguese organizations, etc.
Series X: General
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1908-2013., Extent: 4 boxes. (Box 1-4)
  Correspondence, 1908-2013, of Edith Francisco Buckley consisting of applications, cards, checks, clippings, emails, faxes, invitations, letters, notes, postcards, receipts, and other papers, concerning Peter Francisco and the Society of the Descendants of Peter Francisco, including biographical and genealogical information on Francisco, the operations and programs of the Society, and correspondence from other individuals and organizations regarding Peter Franscisco and the Society.
  - Correspondence, 1908, 1930, 1945-1946, 1957, 1969, 1970-1979. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1989. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-March 1990. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, April-November, no date 1990. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1991. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, July-December, no date 1991. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1992. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1993. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, January-April 1994. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, July-December, no date 1994. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, January-April 1995. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, May-June 1995. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, July-August 1995. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, September-December, no date 1995. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, January-February 1996. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, March 1996. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, April-June 1996. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, July-September 1996. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, October-November 1996. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, December, no date 1996. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, February 1997. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, March 1997. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, April, June 1997. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, July-August 1997. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, September-October 1997. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, November-December, no date 1997. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, January-February 1998. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, March-April 1998. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, May-June 1998. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, July-September 1998. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, October-December 1998. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January-February 1999. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, March 1999. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, April-June 1999. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, July 1999. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, August-September 1999. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, October 1999. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, November-December, no date 1999. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, January-February 2000. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, March 2000. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, April-June 2000. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, July-August 2000. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, September 2000. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, October 2000. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, November-December 2000. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, No date 2000. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, January-February 2001. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, March-April 2001. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, May-June 2001. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, August-November 2001. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, December, no date 2001. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-February 2002. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, March-April 2002. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, May-June 2002. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, July-August 2002. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, September-October 2002. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, November-December, no date 2002. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, January 2003. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, February-March 2003. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, April, June-August 2003. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, September-December, no date 2003. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, January-February 2004. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, March-April 2004. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, May-August 2004. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, September-December, no date 2004. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, January-April 2005. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, May-September 2005. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, October-December, no date 2005. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, January-February 2006. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, March-May 2006. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, June-August 2006. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, September-October 2006. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, No date 2006. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, January-February 2007. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, March-May 2007. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, July-December 2007. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, No date 2007. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, January-February 2008. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, March 2008. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, April-July 2008. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, September 2008. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, October-November 2008. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, No date 2008. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, January-March 2009. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, April 2009. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, May-July 2009. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, August-November, no date 2009. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, January-June 2010. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, July-December, no date 2010. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, January-May 2011. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, June 2011. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, July-August 2011. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, September-November, no date 2011. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, January-6 April 2012. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 13 April-December 2012. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 2013. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, no date. (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Series II: Society of the Descendants of Peter Francisco, 1972-2012., Extent: 4 boxes. (Box 5-8)
  Society of the Descendants of Peter Franscisco (SDPF) consists of the papers of Edith Francisco Buckley as corresponding secretary and as president of the SDPF; papers relating to the general operation of the SDPF; SDPF newsletters; SDPF news releases; papers regarding ownership and restoration of Locust Grove, Peter Francisco's Buckingham County, Virginia, home; and papers regarding the SDPF's annual wreath-laying ceremonies and fall picnic/luncheons.
  - Subseries A: Corresponding Secretary, 1972-1989., 1 box (Box 5)
    Corresponding secretary, 1972-1989, contains the papers of Edith Francisco Buckley while serving as corresponding secretary of the SDPF and includes addresses, certificates, clippings, correspondence, lists, maps, minutes, notes, programs, and other papers. Papers detail the operations and activities of the SDPF.
    - Corresponding secretary, 1972-1973. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Corresponding secretary, 1973-1974. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Corresponding secretary, 1974-1975. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Corresponding secretary, 1975-1976. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Corresponding secretary, 1976-1977. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Corresponding secretary, 1977-1978. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Corresponding secretary, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Corresponding secretary, 1979-1980. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Corresponding secretary, 1980-1981. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Corresponding secretary, 1981-1982. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Corresponding secretary, 1982-1983. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Corresponding secretary, 1983-1984. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Corresponding secretary: artifacts and possessions, 1976-1989. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Subseries B: President, 1984-1987., 1 box (Box 5)
    President, 1984-1987, contains the papers of Edith Francisco Buckley while serving as president of the SDPF and includes addresses, correspondence, minutes, notes, programs, receipts, and other papers. Papers detail the operations and activities of the SDPF.
    - President, 1984. (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - President, 1985. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - President, 1986. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - President, 1987. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Subseries C: SDPF general papers, 1973-2010., 2 boxes (Box 5-6)
    General papers, 1973-2010, contains brochures, by-laws, correspondence, directions, forms, lists of officers, maps, membership applications, notebooks, notes, programs, scrapbooks, stamps, and other papers highlighting the operations and activities of the SDPF.
    - SDPF by-laws. (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Membership applications. (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Officers, 1988, no date. (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - SDPF information and brochures. (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - IRS correspondence, 1975, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Directions and directional maps to meeting places. (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Peter Francisco stamp, 1975-1976. (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Family illness forms, 1979-1991. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - General papers, 1973-2008. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1985-1986. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Notebooks. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Subseries D: Newsletters, 1973-2012., 1 box (Box 6)
    Newsletters, 1973-2012, contain information on the activities of the SDPF.
    - Newsletters, 1973-1978. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Newsletters, 1980-1987. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Newsletters, 2001, 2003, 2005, 2008-2010, 2012. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subseries E: News releases, 1995-2006., 1 box (Box 6)
    News releases, 1995-2006, contains news releases sent to newspapers throughout the state of Virginia to promote the SDPF and its programs and events.
    - News releases, 1995-2000. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - News releases, 2001-2003. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - News releases, 2004-2006. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Subseries F: Locust Grove, 1975-2011., 2 boxes (Box 6-7)
    Locust Grove, 1975-2011, contains agreements, applications, articles, brochures, certificates, clippings, correspondence, lists, notes, reports, and other papers concerning the leasing and preservation of Locust Grove in Buckingham County, home of Peter Francisco. Papers contain correspondence with the Department of Historic Resources for funding, and also contains papers relating to archaeology on-site and to the raising of a historic marker for the site.
    - Locust Grove lease agreements, 1973, 1975. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Owner-architect agreement on restoration, 1975. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Restoration of Locust Grove in the County of Buckingham in the Commonwealth of Virginia Home of Peter Francisco circa 1810, 1975-1976. (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Founder's Certificate forms and design. (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Builders, 1977. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Builders, 1978. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Builders, 1979. (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Builders, 1980. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Builders, 1981-1982. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Builders, no date. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Log containing Locust Grove correspondence, 1977-1981. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1977, 1979, 1981, 1985-1986. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1990-1995. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 2005, 2011, no date. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Virginia Historic Landmoarks Commission correspondence, 1975-1979. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Historic Landmarks Commission/Virginia Department of Conservation and Historic Resources, Division of Historic Landmarks/Virginia Department of Historic Resources correspondence, 1984-1986, 1989. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Virginia Department of Historic Resources, 1990-1993. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Virginia Deparment of Historic Resources--application for funds. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Papers relating to funding restoration. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Historic marker, 1996, 1998-2000, no date. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Dig at Locust Grove (photographs). (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Catching up with the Past: Archeology at Locust Grove from Olde Times, Spring 1988. (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - General papers. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Subseries G: Wreath-laying ceremonies, 1974-2008., 2 boxes (Box 7-8)
    Wreath-laying ceremonies, 1974-2008, consists of correspondence, invitations, notes, programs, and other papers regarding the annual ceremony held by the SDPF every March at the Virginia State Capitol to honor Peter Francisco.
    - Wreath-laying ceremony, 1974-1975, 1978. (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Wreath-laying ceremony, 1986-1987. (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Wreath-laying ceremony, 1990, 1993, 1995-1999. (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Wreath-laying ceremony, 2000-2001. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Wreath-laying ceremony, 2002. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Wreath-laying ceremony, 2003-2004. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Wreath-laying ceremony, 2005-2007. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Wreath-laying ceremony, 2008. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Wreath-laying ceremony, no date. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Subseries H: SDPF picnic/Fall luncheon, 1983-2005., 1 box (Box 8)
    SDPF picnic/Fall luncheon, 1983-2005, contains addresses, agendas, brochures, cards, correspondence, emails, faxes, invitations, minutes, programs, and other papers concerning the picnics/Fall luncheons of the SDPF. Contains information on the SDPF's activities and on Peter Francisco.
    - SDPF picnic, 1983, 1987-1989, 1991, 1993, 1996-1997. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - SDPF picnic, 1998. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - SDPF picnic, 1999-2002. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Fall luncheon, 2003. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Fall luncheon, 2004. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Fall luncheon, 2005. (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Series III: Individuals, 1971-2010., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 8-9)
  Individuals, 1971-2010, contains addresses, articles, biographies, bylaws, cards, chronologies, clippings, correspondence, emails, genealogies, newsletters, obituaries, pictures, proclamations, programs, and other papers, relating to Sallie Edwards Bowman, William Arthur Moon, Louise DeVere, Bruce and Virginia English, and others regarding their activities as members of teh SDPF and/or their research on Peter Francisco and Francisco family genealogy.
  - Subseries A: Sallie Edwards Bowman, 1971-2010., 1 box (Box 8)
    Papers of Sallie Edwards Bowman (1913-2001) of Richmond, Virginia, concerning the SDPF and her research on Peter Franscisco and Francisco family genealogy.
    - Correspondence, 1971-1979. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1981. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1984, 1988-1989. (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1990, 1994, 1996, 1998, 2001, no date. (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - SDPF papers, 1971-1982. (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Peter Francisco biographies. (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Francisco family genealogies. (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Francisco family genealogy research. (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Clippings, 1996, no date. (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Peter Francisco portraits. (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Subseries B: William Arthur Moon, 1978-2006., 1 box (Box 9)
    Papers of William Arthur Moon (1902-1987) of Pfafftown, North Carolina, concerning his research on Peter Francisco, including Moon's trip to Port Judeau, Terceira Island, to determine Francisco's birthplace, and Moon's book Peter Francisco: the Portuguese Patriot.
    - Correspondence, 1978-1983, 1997, 2006. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Port Judeau, Terceira Island--correspondence and articles, 1979-1997. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Articles, pictures, programs and other papers. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Peter Francisco: the Portugues Patriot papers. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Subseries C: Louise DeVere, 1992-2000., 1 box (Box 9)
    Papers of Louise DeVere (1944-2000) of Portsmouth, Virginia, and Athens, Georgia, concerning the SDPF and personal news.
    - Correspondence, 1992-2000. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Obituary, November 2000. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Subseries D: Other individuals, 1999-2008., 1 box (Box 9)
    Obituaries and other related papers of Edmund Dinis (1924-2010), Bruce Vaughan English (1921-2008), Virginia McCall Shaw English (1909=2006), and Jabez Quintus Massie (1905-2007). Also contains tributes and obituaries members of the SDPF who had died.
    - Edmund Dinis obituary, etc., 1999, 2010. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Bruce Vaughan English obituary, January 2008, undated. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Virginia McCall Shaw English obituary and other papers, October 2006, April 2007. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Jabez Quintus Massie obituary, February 2007. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Obituaries, memorials, letters, 2002, 2006-2007, no date. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - In tribute--wreath-laying ceremony, 18 March 2007. (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Series IV: Photographs., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 9-10)
  Photographs of Edith Francisco Buckley, the SDPF, and Locust Grove, highlighting Buckley's and the SDPF's activities honoring Peter Franscisco and work on Locust Grove, Peter Francisco's Buckingham County home.
  - Wreath-laying, 1998, 2002. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Wreath-laying, 2001. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Meetings[?]. (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Locust Grove (folder 1 of 5)--before and after completion. (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Locust Grove (folder 2 of 5)--SDPF picnic,. (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Locust Grove (folder 3 of 5). (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Locust Grove (folder 4 of 5). (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Locust Grove (folder 5 of 5). (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Peter Francisco portraits. (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Peter Francisco monument and stamp unveiling, 1975. (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Azores--Port Judeau, Terceira Island. (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - City Point (Hopewell, Virginia). (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Guilford Court House battlefield. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Legends Walk. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Brooke's Bank (Essex County), Hunting Tower (Buckingham County)--drawing, and Westcreek--Ben Ward's Tavern site (Nottoway County). (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Portuguese Continental Union. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Margaret Francisco Anderson, 101 East Ky (no location), and Francisco family reunion (first?). (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Arthur Ramposo. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous photographs. (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Series V: Addresses and talks, 1976-2010., Extent: 1 box. (Box 10)
  Addresses and talks, 1976-2010, on both Peter Francisco and on the SDPF delivered by Edith Francisco Buckley and others to both the SDPF and to outside organizations.
  - Addresses and talks, 1976-2010. (Box 10, Folder 9)